Marking releases with tags gives one more bonus.
For example, we need to publish a release
or just a current version of the project
for someone to read. Not as a whole repository
but as an archive of files.
"git describe" command allows to get a description
based on the closest tag by any commit given.
Only annotated tags are used by default,
albeit one can use options to allow any tags.
For example "git describe" and this commit, see?
Not commit by the tag as we saw earlier,
but the other way around, tag by commit
Here it is for the other commit or just "git describe"
which will describe the "HEAD" with no arguements given.
Heres a more interesting one, we are in the "feature"
there is no tag here and therefore "describe" finds the closest tag,
shows how many commits are we ahead,
2 commits actually, and then "g"
with a shortened identifier of the described commit.
Given this description
we can use it in a "git archive" command.
This command creates an archive from whats in the repository
at the moment of the commit provided, in our case we need
lets say "HEAD"
and "-o" flag allows us to specify the destination path
of this archive, in the "/tmp" directory.
And this is the name of the archived file.
executing...
Done!
Now, lets open that folder "cd /tmp"
Lets see what do we have here?
You see, we really have an archive for the "HEAD"
and due to "describe" and the tags we can easily identify
the release it belongs to, including,
as in our case, the version which is not a release
on its own.